A Guide to the Baylor Family Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
James Bowen Baylor (1849-1924) graduated with an engineering degree from the University of Virginia in 1872 and was appointed an aid in the United States Coast and Geodetic Survey Department in 1874, continuing to work as a field agent throughout his career. His many assignments included: the determination of the elements of earth's magnetism from Canada to Mexico; the survey of oyster grounds in Louisiana and Virginia, 1889-1894; his appointment as a Commissioner of the United States Supreme Court to settle the Virginia - Tennessee boundary line dispute, establishing it in the middle of Main Street, Bristol, 1900-1902; and also the establishment of boundaries between Virginia and Maryland, New York and Pennsylvania, and the United States and Canada.
The Oyster Industry Protection Correspondence contains much correspondence from William Ellinger of Fox Island, Virginia, who describes himself as an oyster planter. Printed material consists of death notices for United States Coast and Geodetic Survey men, Richard D. Cutts and Benjamin Peirce (1880& 1883), and three pamphlets concerning the United States and Canadian boundary, the oyster laws of Virginia, and a Virginia Military Institute valedictory address by Edward Hutson Russell.
Oversize items include a survey of the lands of John Roy Baylor (June 1847), photographs of the United States Coast and Geodetic Survey, and a printed plan of the fairgrounds of the Virginia State Agricultural Society, Richmond, 1854.
The three Baylor family ledgers, 1719-1755, contain many references to the purchase of slaves (see addendum).
ADDENDUM RE THE BAYLOR LEDGERS
The three Baylor family ledgers contain many references concerning tobacco exports, the purchase of merchandise, work done on various ships, and slaves, which at times had their place of origin noted, as in " Madigaschar woman," "man of Callabar, " and " Barbadoes negro." The accounts of the first two ledgers are indexed in the front of the volumes.
References to slavery occurring in volume one include the following pages: 12, 13, 15, 17, 22-24, 26, 28, 35, 37, 39, 47, 49, 64-66, 68, 70-71, 77, 80-81, 83, 92-93, 101-102, 113-114, 127, 130, 134, 166, & 175. References to slavery in volume two include: 10, 16, 30, 34, 56, 63-64, 74, 86, 88, 102, 115, 123, 134, 183, & 207. Volume three pages include: 40, 71, 124, 130, 132, 135, 146, 148, 152-153, & 155.
Occasionally the names of the slave ships and other vessels are recorded in the ledgers with notes on the contents purchased from them. These, along with their volume and page number, are listed below.
Ann & Sarah 1.96, 139, 150, & 155
Berkeley 1.38, 64, 71, 98, 121, 149, & 167; & 2.50
Betty 1.94
Callabar 1.39, 68, & 98; & 2.96, 111, 136
Greyhound 1.23, 37, 38, 65, 92, & 96; & 2.4, 54, & 97
Hunter 1.68
Little John 1.9, 10, 12, 25, & 75; & 2.116 & 136
Little York 2.124
Lucy 1.94 & 149
Mattapony Pink 1.9, 33, 94, 99, 135, 145, 158, 180, & 185
Nassopenex Sloop 1.2, 5, 38, & 75
Parnel Galley 2.22
Prince Eugene 1.139, 150, & 162-164
Twerton 1.15, 39, 103, & 2.90
Other entries include: the Iron Mine Adventurers 1.1 & 1.11; horses 1.28; the Germana mines 2.188; John Baylor's estate 2.73 & 131; quitrents for land in Caroline County, Spotsylvania County, Orange County, and King and Queen County 2.34 & 79; and doctor and midwife accounts 3.120-121, 142, & 149. Volume three also has many references to the manufacture and repair of hardware, utensils, and agricultural equipment. In addition, at the end of the last volume, there is a list of memoranda concerning agreements and contracts of John Baylor, a memorandum of slaves sold off W. Lyde's plantation (November 30, 1742) and a list of all the Negroes belonging to Baylor in 1744.
Organization
The Baylor Family Papers have been arranged in the following six series:
I. Correspondence (Box 1)
II. Legal and Financial Papers (Boxes 2-3)
III. Miscellaneous Papers (Box 4)
IV. Notebooks and Bound Volumes (Boxes 5-7)
V. Papers of James B. Baylor and the United States Coast & Geodetic Survey (Boxes 8-11)
VI. Oversize Items & 2M Volumes
Contents List
- SERIES I: CORRESPONDENCE
  - Correspondence., 1741-1900, & n.d.; (11 folders) (Box Box 1)
- SERIES II: LEGAL & FINANCIAL PAPERS
  - Amnesty Papers of John Roy Baylor., 1865 (Box Box 2)
  - Land Plats and Surveys., 1701-1841 (Box Box 2)
  - Legal Papers., 1653-1914, & n.d.; (4 folders) (Box Box 2)
  - Wills of John Baylor (1705-1772)., 1770 Feb 19 (Box Box 2)
  - Frances Baylor (1760-1815) copies., 1815 June 12 (Box Box 2)
  - Account Books of John Roy Baylor., 1859-1870 (Box Box 2)
  - Bank Statements & Canceled Check Samples., 1882-1895 (Box Box 2)
  - Farm Book., 1896-1899 (Box Box 3)
  - Financial Papers., 1714-1896, & n.d.; (9 folders) (Box Box 3)
  - John Baylor's Receipt Book., 1792-1795 (Box Box 3)
- SERIES III: MISCELLANEOUS PAPERS
  - Diary of a Journey from "Newmarket" to Warm Springs, Augusta County, Virginia by John Baylor., 1780 (Box Box 4)
  - Genealogical Material., ca. 1835-1860, & n.d. (Box Box 4)
  - "A History of the Early Church in Virginia"., n.d (Box Box 4)
  - Literary Compositions of Maria R. Baylor., [ca.1885] (Box Box 4)
  - Memorandum Book of John Baylor (1750-1808) re the beginning of a voyage on the Potomack and a description of the saltworks at Portsmouth, [England]., 1775 Oct-1778 Mar (Box Box 4)
  - Military Papers., 1756, 1777-1782, 1814, & n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Papers., 1771-1959 (Box Box 4)
  - Newsclippings., 1921-1933, & n.d. (Box Box 4)
  - Photographs., [ca. 1870-1900] (Box Box 4)
- SERIES IV: NOTEBOOKS AND BOUND VOLUMES
  - Photograph Album of John Roy Baylor., 1887 Dec 25 (Box Box 5)
  - French Notebooks of Maria Roy Baylor., n.d. (Box Box 5)
  - German Notebook of Maria Roy Baylor., n.d (Box Box 5)
  - Latin Notebooks of Maria Roy Baylor., n.d (Box Box 5)
  - Spelling Notebook of Frank Blackford., n.d (Box Box 5)
  - Dr. John Roy Baylor's Genealogical and Historical Notebook., 1872 (Box Box 6)
  - Dr. John Roy Baylor Medical Notebook and Farm Expense Book., 1847-1851 (Box Box 6)
  - University of Virginia Chemistry Notebook of James B.Baylor., ca. 1870 (Box Box 6)
  - Farm Account Book., 1856-1892 (Box Box 6)
  - Expense Book., 1898-1899 (Box Box 6)
  - Engineering Notebook of James B. Baylor, with accounts., 1879-1892, & n.d. (Box Box 6)
  - Account Book of Dr. John Roy Baylor., 1868-1874 (Box Box 6)
  - Scrapbook of John Roy Baylor of newsclippings., 1855-1897 (Box Box 6)
  - Scrapbook of Newsclippings., 1858-1867 (Box Box 7)
  - Farm Book of Dr. John Roy Baylor., 1847-1868 (Box Box 7)
  - Letters of Junius, hand copied by John Baylor., 1769-1771 (Box Box 7)
- SERIES V: JAMES B. BAYLOR & THE U.S. COAST & GEODETIC SURVEY
  - Accounts and Receipts., 1903, & 1912-1915 (Box Box 8)
  - Circulars., 1879-1909 (Box Box 8)
  - Correspondence and Reports of James Baylor., 1874-1909; (7 folders) (Box Box 8)
  - Correspondence and Reports of James B. Baylor., 1911-1915, & n.d.; (3 folders) (Box Box 9)
  - Fort Morgan, Baldwin County, Alabama., 1892 (Box Box 9)
  - Oyster Industry Protection Correspondence., 1891-1895; (2 folders) (Box Box 9)
  - Oyster Survey Alphabetical Correspondence, A-Z., 1891-1895; (3 folders) (Box Box 9)
  - Photographs., ca. 1908-1913 (Box Box 9)
  - Printed Material., 1880-1908 (Box Box 10)
  - Property Inventory., 1889-1892, & 1906-1913 (Box Box 10)
  - Tangier Sound., 1891 (Box Box 10)
  - Transverse at Mobile Bay., 1879 (Box Box 10)
  - U.S.Coast & Geodetic Survey - Abstract of Expenditures and Vouchers., 1892 & 1903 (Box Box 10)
  - U.S.& Canada Boundary Survey - Vouchers., 1908-1909 (Box Box 10)
  - U.S.& Canada Boundary Survey - Abstract of Expenditures.., 1908-1910 (Box Box 10)
  - U.S.& Canada Boundary Survey - Abstract of Expenditures and Vouchers., 1911-1931 (Box Box 10)
  - Virginia and Tennessee Original Boundary Records., 1902; (4 volumes) (Box Box 11)
  - Account Book of James B. Baylor with the U.S. Coast Survey., 1892 (Box Box 11)
  - Property Inventory., 1910-1911 (Box Box 11)
  - Observations of Horizontal Angles., 1904 (Box Box 11)
- SERIES VI: OVERSIZE ITEMS & 2M VOLUMES
  - Baylor Ledgers., 1719-1744; (3 volumes)
  - Survey of John Roy Baylor's land at "Newmarket"., 1847 Jun (Oversize M18)
  - Printed Plan of the Fairgrounds of the Virginia State Agricultural Society, Richmond., 1854 (Oversize M18)
  - Photographs of the U.S.Coast and Geodetic Survey. (Oversize M18)